{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This group ceded control of the Bug River to Lithuania at the Battle of the Blue Waters. The Stand on the Ugra River symbolically marked the end of this group’s power, though it had earlier lost the Battle of Kulikovo to Dmitri Donskoy. This group once filled nine sacks with ears after defeating Henry the Pious at the Battle of Legnica [leg-neetz-ah]. This group was founded by Batu and forced Russia to pay tribute to the khan. For ten points, name this Mongol horde named for the color of its troops’ tents.",
      "answer": [
        "Golden Horde",
        "Kipchat Khanate",
        "Ulus of Jochi",
        "propmt on the Mongols"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event, which inspired Michael Tippet’s oratorio A Child of Our Time, caused many people to flee to the Restricted Sector for Stateless Refugees in Shanghai. Reinhard Heydrich sent a secret telegram with instructions for this event, which included the arrests of tens of thousands of men. This event began on November 9th, exactly fifteen years after the Beer Hall Putsch, and featured mass looting of stores and burning of synagogues. For ten points, name this 1938 attack on German Jews, named for the shards of glass that flew during it.",
      "answer": [
        "Kristallnacht",
        "Night of Broken Glass before “glass” is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This practice is often said to have begun in America with a Northampton County court case between Anthony Johnson and Robert Parker. John Punch is sometimes seen as the first American subject of this practice, which the Code Noir, requiring Catholic education, established in New France. A series of Virginia codes in 1705 defined this state as applying to anyone not belonging to a Christian nation. For ten points, name this practice that began with indentured servants of African descent.",
      "answer": [
        "slavery",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After the winning side in this war gained naval superiority, they invaded and controlled Tarapac´a. During this war’s Battle of Iquique [ee-kee-kay], the Esmeralda was sunk by the Huascar, an ironclad commaned by Miguel Grau. The Treaty of Ancon took one country out of this war, in which the Atacama Desert was the site of land battles. Control of saltpeter resources was a primary cause of, for ten points, what late 19th century war that Peru and Bolivia lost to Chile, named for the oceanic coast they shared?",
      "answer": [
        "War of the Pacific",
        "Saltpeter War before it is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s suburb of Blachernae became the site of the royal palace after the rule of Manuel I. The Galata neighborhood near this city was populated by Italian traders and was the site of a namesake tower that controlled a large sea chain. This city, which was protected by the Theodosian Walls, was sacked during the Fourth Crusade and captured in 1453 by Mehmed II. The Hagia Sophia is in, for ten points, what city on the Bosporus, the capital of the Byzantine Empire?",
      "answer": "Constantinople"
    },
    {
      "question": "David Harris founded an organization called The Resistance to assist in this action. Ted Nugent took meth and urinated on himself in order to commit this action, while James Fallows committed it by lowering his body weight. Joining the Coast Guard and moving to Canada were common methods of performing this action, which led to the arrest of Muhammad Ali. Gerald Ford issued amnesty for those who committed, for ten points, what action instead of fighting in Vietnam?",
      "answer": [
        "dodging the draft during the Vietnam War",
        "equivalent answers that specifically mention the draft"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events caused the wreck of the George L. Newman, since the ship was unable to spot a lighthouse on Green Island. Some scientists theorize that Biela’s Comet caused one of these events in the city of Peshtigo. Another event of this type was allegedly worsened after Daniel “Peg Leg” Sullivan let a group of animals out of a barn; that event legendarily began after one of Catherine O’Leary’s cows kicked over a lantern. For ten points, name this type of disaster that devastated Chicago in 1871.",
      "answer": "fires"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sculptures found in temples in Kerala depict lasya, a gentle form of this activity. Ernest Mackay found a depiction of a figure engaged in this activity who wears roughly 30 bangles. A 9th century sculpture found inside a temple in Nallur shows a deity as “Nataraja,” meaning the lord of this activity. At Mohenjo-Daro, a bronze statue of a girl engaging in this activity was discovered in 1926. Sattriya is among the classical forms of this activity in India in which the performer enacts a story. For ten points, name this performing art involving moving to the rhythm of music.",
      "answer": "dancing"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler integrated the laws of king Ine and Offa into his own codex, which became known as the Doom Book. This man established the southern boundary of the Danelaw after forcing his enemies into the Treaty of Wedmore, and he forced Guthrum to convert to Christianity after the Battle of Edington. Wessex’s power was greatly expanded by, for ten points, what ninth century English king known as “the Great?”",
      "answer": "Alfred the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "After Lyndon Johnson unveiled the Great Society at a speech at Ohio University, he more formally outlined its proposals at a speech at this university. The John F. Kennedy speech that first publicly outlined the Peace Corps was given at this university. The case Grutter v. Bollinger founded that racial preferences in this university’s law school admissions did not constitute a quota. For ten points, name this university that moved to Ann Arbor in 1837 after originally being founded in Detroit.",
      "answer": "University of Michigan Ann Arbor"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This President’s administration attempted to curb the arrival of communists by passing the Per Centum Act, which limited yearly immigration to 3% of a current ethnicity’s population. After this man was nominated at the Blackstone Hotel in a “smoke filled room,” he routed James Cox in the general election. Secretary Albert Fall’s sale of Navy land in the Teapot Dome scandal tarnished the legacy of, for ten points, what US president who promised a “return to normalcy” in the election of 1920?",
        "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both candidates in 1920, Harding and James Cox, hailed from this state, as did Harding advisors Joseph Foraker and Harry Daugherty.",
        "answer": "Ohio"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2015, 30 people were detained in this country during the “709” crackdown on lawyers. This country’s government has been accused of harvesting organs from members of a religious group symbolized by a Dharma Wheel. An activist from this country was awarded the 2010 Nobel Prize while imprisoned for the crime of “Inciting subversion of state power.” The Uyghur [wee-gur] minority has suffered persecution in, for ten points, what country whose government cracked down on the Tiananmen Square protests in Beijing?",
        "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Buddhist-inspired religious movement, whose emblem is the Dharma Wheel, has been persecuted in China since the mid-1990s. Li Hongzhi, who lives in exile in New York, was one of the founders of this movement.",
        "answer": "Falun Gong or Falun Dafa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s winning commander allegedly stated “let the boy win his spurs” when he was told his son was under attack. An angered Count of Alen¸con attacked his own Genoese mercenaries in this battle after heavy rain ruined their crossbows. This battle led Calais [kah-lay] to fall into foreign hands for over two hundred years. Like the later Battle of Agincourt, the winners of this battle used the longbow to render cavalry ineffective. For ten points, name this 1346 victory for England in the Hundred Years War.",
        "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This “boy,” the son of Edward III, was given the chance to “win his spurs” at Crecy.",
        "answer": [
          "Edward the Black Prince",
          "Edward of Woodstock"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Douglas Hofstadter’s massive work Le Ton Beau de Marot is a set of reflections on this activity. Walter Benjamin wrote an essay titled for the “Task” of someone who performs this activity. When doing this action, one sometimes must choose whether to prioritize literal or stylistic accuracy. The discovery of the Rosetta Stone allowed this to be done with Egyptian sources for the first time. For ten points, name this process of rendering texts from one language into another.",
        "answer": [
          "translation",
          "word forms",
          "translating poetry, based on the first clue"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Max Muller was a prominent translator of works in this ancient language, whose shared roots with Latin and Greek were the first suggestion of the Indo-European language family.",
        "answer": "Sanskrit"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Segregation in this state’s schooling system prompted the case Gebhart v. Belton. A Huguenot expert in gunpowder manufacturing established a company in this state near a city along the Brandywine River; that company is DuPont. After arriving aboard the Kalmar Nyckel, Peter Minuit established Fort Christina in what is now, for ten points, what first state to ratify the Constitution, a state that is home to Dover?",
        "answer": "Delaware"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Despite being founded by former Director of New Netherland Peter Minuit, Fort Christina was the first American settlement of this European country. A dedication of Fort Christina’s grounds as a park in 1938 was attended by this country’s then-Crown Prince, Gustaf Adolf.",
        "answer": "Sweden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After Bob Hepple’s charges were dismissed during this trial, he fled overseas. Judge Quartus de Vet presided over this trial, which listed Denis Goldberg and Walter Sisulu among the 11 accused. The main target of this event, who was arrested at Liliesleaf Farm, was sentenced to 18 years on Robben Island and a total of 27 years imprisonment before his release by F.W. de Klerk. For ten points, name this 1960s trial that convicted Nelson Mandela.",
        "answer": "Rivonia Trial"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After being convicted at Rivonia, Nelson Mandela gave this speech, in which he noted “I have cherished the ideal of a democratic and free society.”",
        "answer": "“I am Prepared to Die” speech"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man helped reinstate Phocis as the Oracle of Delphi during the Second Sacred War. This man faced a revolt in Miletus, which partly caused this lover of Aspasia to transfer funds from the treasury of the Delian League to his city. Thucydides recorded a famous funeral oration given by this man during the first year of a lengthy war against Sparta. For ten points, name this statesman who led during the Golden Age of Athens and the start of the Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Pericles BONUS:AccordingtothisGreekcomicplaywright’sThe Archanians,Pericles’consortAspasiasupposedly convinced him to issue the Megarian Decree. This author’s anti-war plays include Lysistrata. ANSWER: Aristophanes 8 In this year, Patrick Dunn helped organize a demonstration in Tompkins Square that police brutally repressed. The collapse of Jay Cooke & Company, which was unable to sell enough bonds in Northern Pacific Railway, helped trigger a financial crisis in this year, as did the passage of a Coinage Act that became known as the “Crime of” this year. For ten points, name this year in which an economic panic struck the US during the Grant administration. ANSWER: 1873"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This senator from Ohio introduced the Coinage Act of 1873 and served as treasury secretary under Rutherford B. Hayes.",
        "answer": "John Sherman"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Journalists",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival of ABC and NBC whose Evening News was anchored by Walter Cronkite.",
          "answer": [
            "CBS",
            "Columbia Broadcasting System"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Publisher of the New York World and namesake of annual prizes for journalism, literature, and music.",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph Pulitzer",
            "Pulitzer Prize"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Owner of the New York Journal and rival of that publisher, famous for “providing” the Spanish- American War with yellow journalism.",
          "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the authors of All the President’s Men who investigated Watergate for the Washington Post.",
          "answer": "Bob Woodward and/or Carl Bernstein"
        },
        {
          "question": "German-born publisher who was acquitted of libel in New York in 1735.",
          "answer": "John Peter Zenger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muckraker whose flash photographs were collected in How the Other Half Lives.",
          "answer": "Jacob Riis"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Sage of Baltimore,” a satirist who covered the Scopes Trial",
          "answer": "Henry Louis “H.L.” Mencken"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-founder of the NAACP who researched lynching in Memphis until a white mob burned down her office.",
          "answer": "Ida B. Wells"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Communism in Europe",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Final leader of the Soviet Union; he was succeeded by Boris Yeltsin.",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Faction of communists during the Russian Revolution who prevailed over the Mensheviks.",
          "answer": [
            "Bolsheviks",
            "Bolshevists"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of political liberalization in Czechoslovakia that began after the election of Alexander Dubˇcek [doob-check] in 1968.",
          "answer": "Prague Spring"
        },
        {
          "question": "Collective defense treaty signed by eight communist countries after World War II, created in response to NATO.",
          "answer": "Warsaw Pact"
        },
        {
          "question": "East German secret police service whose name is an abbreviation of the German for “State Security Service.”",
          "answer": "Stasi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician and labour activist who founded the Soviet Bloc’s first independent trade union, known as Solidarity.",
          "answer": "Lech Walesa , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Communist dictator and “Conducator” of Romania during World War II",
          "answer": "Ion Antonescu"
        },
        {
          "question": "First communist leader of Bulgaria; he was initially arrested for the Reichstag fire in 1933.",
          "answer": "Georgi Dimitrov"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Six Day War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Global organization that was led by U Thant during the war and which withdrew forces prior to the war.",
          "answer": "United Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian peninsula, east of the Red Sea, that was seized by Israel.",
          "answer": "Sinai Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of heights that Israel seized from Syria during the war.",
          "answer": "Golan Heights"
        },
        {
          "question": "Straits on the Gulf of Aqaba that Egypt closed to Israeli shipping, triggering the war.",
          "answer": "Straits of Tiran"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of military action that Israel performed in Operation Focus to open the war.",
          "answer": "pre-emptive air strike"
        },
        {
          "question": "Israeli line of fortifications built along the Suez Canal after the war; it was overrun in 1973.",
          "answer": "Bar Lev Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "American research ship that was attacked by Israel in a friendly fire incident during the war.",
          "answer": "USS Liberty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Israeli Prime Minister during the war; he died in office two years later.",
          "answer": "Levi Eshkol"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A version of this document displayed in Palaestina Prima provided the source material for Eusebius of Caesaria’s translation in his Historia Ecclesiastica. The city for which this document is named used to be called (20 pts)",
        "Mediolanum. Property was given back to the affected group of this document, who had been the subject of (10 pts)",
        "persecutions under emperors like Diocletian and Nero. Constantine created, for ten points, what edict promoting tolerance toward Christians?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edict of Milan",
        "Edictum Mediolanense until “Mediolanum” is read",
        "prompt after"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At this battle, a steamboat called the Tigress was taken to Crump’s Landing to order a division leader to stand by. The USS Tyler and USS Lexington provided support for one side’s movements along a river near the battlefield of this battle, where (20 pts)",
        "P.G.T. Beauregard launched an attack from Corinth, Mississippi. Albert Sidney Johnston was killed at this battle, in which heavy fighting took place at the (10 pts)",
        "Hornet’s Nest. A major goal of this battle was to cut off a railroad to Richmond that began in Memphis. For ten points, name this 1862 Civil War battle fought in Tennessee."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Shiloh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Woodward Commission was tasked with overseeing the land rights of these people, whose right to serve in the military was championed by Jack Patten. The Christian Missionary Society attempted to dissolve a conflict involving these people that came to be known as the Caledon Bay crisis. (20 pts)",
        "Arnhem Land is largely inhabited by these people, who are the subject of National Sorry Day. The displaced (10 pts)",
        "children of these people came to be known as “Stolen Generations.” Over 4 percent of the population of Queensland is, for ten points, what group of indigenous Australians?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Aboriginal Australians or Aborigines",
        "Stolen Generations before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One country entered this war with Felix Schwarzenberg’s declaration that “Austria shall shock the world with the depth of its ingratitude,” before turning on a former ally. This war was prompted when one nation sent the gunship Charlemagne, a violation of the (20 pts)",
        "London Straits Convention. This war, which featured an early engagement at Alma, culminated in the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Balaclava, where Lord Cardigan’s cavalry made a fateful charge. The Charge of the Light Brigade took place in, for ten points, what war fought on a peninsula on the Black Sea?"
      ],
      "answer": "Crimean War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A monk in this work claims that The Palaces of the Patriarch is the setting of the seventh scene of this play, in which Pimen writes a history of his native country. Nikolay Karamzin was one of the writers who inspired this (20 pts)",
        "1825 work, in which an army is led by Grigory against the title character, who had previously served as a boyar before the death of (10 pts)",
        "Dmitri. The Time of Troubles is the background of, for ten points, what play about a Russian tsar, written by Alexander Pushkin?"
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Godunov"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s speech at the University of Kansas stated that the gross domestic product “measures everything except that which is worthwhile.” This man, who cited a man who gave a “ripple of hope” to South Africa in his “Day of (20 pts)",
        "Affirmation” speech, wrote the book The Enemy Within about his efforts fighting the Teamsters in court. This politician was trailing (10 pts)",
        "Eugene McCarthy in the presidential primaries when Sirhan Sirhan assassinated him in Los Angeles. For ten points, name this man who served as attorney general under his brother John."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Robert Francis Kennedy",
        "Bobby Kennedy",
        "RFK"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man called the rapid spread of angiosperms during the Cretaceous Period an “abominable mystery” in a letter to the director of the Kew Gardens, Joseph Hooker. Upon receiving a plant from Madagascar, this man predicted the existence of a pollinator moth that (20 pts)",
        "evolved along with it in his Fertilization of Orchids. Syms Covington and Robert FitzRoy helped this man collect specimens that (10 pts)",
        "ornithologist John Gould later determined to be separate species of Galapagos finches. The theory of natural selection was pioneered by, for ten points, what author of On the Origin of Species?"
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Darwin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Gevork Vartanian discovered a plot by Ernst Kaltenbrunner to assassinate the attendees of this event. During this event, the Partisans were pledged support in their conflict with the Chetniks. After this event, a declaration was issued noting how the participants left it as “friends, in fact, in spirit and in purpose.” The Sword of (20 pts)",
        "Stalingrad was given as a gift during this event, where the details of Operation Overlord were discussed. This event marked the (10 pts)",
        "first time that Franklin Roosevelt met Joseph Stalin. For ten points, name this first conference of the “Big Three,” held in 1943 in the Iranian capital."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tehran Conference",
        "Eureka"
      ]
    }
  ]
}